<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='/build/web.xsl'?>

<rsml version="1.0" language="en"
      xmlns="https://kekkan.org/RsML">
  <meta>
    <title>Tiny TeX Distribution Based on Web2C and LuaTeX</title>
    <subtitle>An Attempt on Minifying TeX</subtitle>
    <author>Jing Huang</author>
    <date>
      <year>2024</year>
      <month>--12</month>
      <day>---20</day>
    </date>
  </meta>

  <unit role="chapter">
    <heading>Why Build a New TeX Distribution</heading>
    <paragraph><emphasize>Finally</emphasize> I decided to build my
    own TeX distribution<footnote>Thanks to LdBeth for
    advertising!</footnote>, as the current TeXLive (even the minimal
    installation) is too bloated for me. All I need is a basic TeX
    compiler and a compact directory containing the files TeX reads
    in. I use Type1 fonts, but I certainly don<apostrophe/>t need a
    command line tool to generate font maps for me.
    <verbatim>ls-R</verbatim> database is unnecessary unless there are
    <emphasize>many</emphasize> files under the directory Kpathsea
    searches<footnote>Which is the case for
    TeXLive.</footnote>. Strictly speaking, I also don<apostrophe/>t
    need LaTeX2e.</paragraph>
  </unit>

  <unit role="chapter">
    <heading>My Choice</heading>
    <paragraph>I chose LuaTeX as the TeX engine. While it
    doesn<apostrophe/>t come with many fancy features out of the box,
    its functionality can be greatly extended using the embedded Lua
    scripting language. As the successor to Omega/Aleph, LuaTeX
    greatly enhances vanilla TeX<apostrophe/>s multilingual
    typesetting capabilities. A build-in graphic library
    <verbatim>mplib</verbatim> is included, which eliminates the need
    for TikZ and such.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>The default format is plainTeX, which I found much
    easier to work with compared to LaTeX2e. It doesn<apostrophe/>t
    involve many high-level abstractions (i.e., NFSS2 for font
    selection), making it more straightforward. It also
    doesn<apostrophe/>t uselessly try to separate format and content,
    which is really useless when doing
    <emphasize>non-trivial</emphasize> typesetting. There are some
    drawbacks though, such as a less active community.</paragraph>
  </unit>

  <unit role="chapter">
    <heading>Construction</heading>

    <unit role="section">
      <heading>Web2C (Kpathsea)</heading>
      <paragraph>The main focus here is on optimizing compile-time and
      runtime path configuration. This is where I modified the
      standard TDS. In addition to optimizing file scanning, I removed
      support for engines other than LuaTeX and eliminated support for
      most helper scripts.</paragraph>
    </unit>

    <unit role="section">
      <heading>Engine (LuaTeX)</heading>
      <paragraph>Nothing special here. I simply compiled LuaTeX inside
      TeXLive<apostrophe/>s source tree (and its banner remains) with
      HarfBuzz. I had tried embedding LuaJIT, but seems like it is
      incompatible with so many Lua-based macro-packages (like
      <verbatim>luaotfload</verbatim>).</paragraph>
    </unit>

    <unit role="section">
      <heading>Fonts and Format</heading>
      <paragraph>The basic installation includes only the Type1 and
      TFM for Computer Modern and all fonts included in the AMSFonts
      bundle. You can use them with the good old ways. In further
      versions, the Concrete Math font might be included.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>To use OpenType or TrueType fonts, you will need
      <verbatim>luaotfload</verbatim>, a font loader adapted from
      ConTeXt for plainTeX. This is bundled in the
      <verbatim>dist.tar.gz</verbatim> which is released with
      <term>aplTeX</term>.</paragraph>
      <paragraph>The default format is plainTeX, which has been
      patched in a way to utilize the extensions of eTeX, pdfTeX, and
      LuaTeX. It is also Unicode-aware. Additionally, I<apostrophe/>ve
      added an <verbatim>\everyjob</verbatim> hook so that LuaTeX will
      read <verbatim>luatex.map</verbatim><footnote>Rather than the
      frustrating
      <verbatim>pdftex.map</verbatim>.</footnote>.</paragraph>
    </unit>
  </unit>

  <unit role="chapter">
    <heading>Dist Release</heading>
    <paragraph>The poor man<apostrophe/>s version doesn<apostrophe/>t
    come with any macro-packages — only plainTeX. I believe external
    macro-packages are generally unnecessary for plainTeX, except in a
    few cases.</paragraph>
    <paragraph>For these rare cases, I<apostrophe/>ve packaged a few
    macro-packages. These are mainly for demonstration purposes
    (showing how the modified TDS works), and to handle some of the
    complex dependencies (many of which weren<apostrophe/>t even
    documented). The packaged ones include:</paragraph>
    <list type="itemize">
      <item><verbatim>luamplib</verbatim>, which offers a convenient
      way to use LuaTeX<apostrophe/>s <verbatim>mplib</verbatim> for
      plotting.</item>
      <item><verbatim>luaotfload</verbatim>, which is the plainTeX
      migration of the ConTeXt font loader, making it easier to work
      with OTF fonts.</item>
      <item><verbatim>luatexja</verbatim>, which provides high-quality
      CJK typesetting support.</item>
    </list>
  </unit>
</rsml>
